Mikhail Kalinin: Hi, Roberto. Hello, Dmitrii.
Dmitrii Shmatko: Hello, Mikhail. Hello, Roberto.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, as usual, we'll wait for, I don't know, maybe 4 to 5 minutes.
Mikhail Kalinin: For more people to come.
Mikhail Kalinin: Morning, Justin.
Justin Traglia: Good morning.
Mikhail Kalinin: Hi, everyone.
Mikhail Kalinin: We'll wait for… Or more minutes.
Mikhail Kalinin: To let people come.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright, let's go ahead and get started.
Mikhail Kalinin: Everyone, welcome to the bus Confirmation Rule.
Mikhail Kalinin: Breakout number 12.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, here is the agenda.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, before we start, I would like to say that this is going to be the last recurring
Mikhail Kalinin: Breakout for fast Confirmation.
Mikhail Kalinin: stuff, so… Yeah, and, we have a…
Mikhail Kalinin: Several items on the agenda to cover today.
Mikhail Kalinin: I believe that if there will be a demand on
Mikhail Kalinin: Any breakout session in the future, we can organize some ad hoc call.
Mikhail Kalinin: But… As long as I can see, we made a great progress so far.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, yeah, this call might be already not that important.
Mikhail Kalinin: To have it, like, on a recurring basis. Okay, so…
Mikhail Kalinin: And yeah, today we'll start with, as usual, with client updates.
Mikhail Kalinin: So… Let's start from Grandine.
Boma: Hello, good afternoon. So, the oldest on Ireland is…
Boma: I updated the test cases, and we only have, like, 3 tests filling, which is…
Boma: part of the spec issue that was opened. So, once we get,
Boma: the particular version, the release, it should pass in our own end, so… but…
Boma: the PR is ready, and then I'm also hoping for PVAS to review, because he was…
Boma: reviewing the PR, for… I was asked to take, switch the branches to Glamsterdam.
Boma: That's all.
Mikhail Kalinin: Great, yeah, great. Yeah, there are issues with the tests, we'll cover this today. I believe that all the PRs emerge now.
Mikhail Kalinin: So… So you should pass the test with the new test vectors.
Mikhail Kalinin: I hope.
Mikhail Kalinin: I have a question, did you…
Mikhail Kalinin: Did you run your implementation on the mainnet?
Mikhail Kalinin: You try…
Boma: No, no, just, LeCore.net.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, just, you know, curious about the main app.
Mikhail Kalinin: Boom.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay, cool. Because, there was, there were some issues with other client implementations in the past, so I think, like, mainnet is a kind of, like, smoke test.
Mikhail Kalinin: For… for… Or FCR.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright.
Mikhail Kalinin: Thanks for… thanks a lot for the update, and let's move to… Lodestar.
Nazar Hussain: So, last… We've, like, a lot.
Nazar Hussain: After our last breakout call, I…
Nazar Hussain: was working on some of our integration, like, a spec test, and I found some
Nazar Hussain: small, minor details that I opened the PR.
Nazar Hussain: thank Mikhail for their review, and those BRs are merged.
Nazar Hussain: Yeah, now I will dig further, once that… those PR are released, and I will,
Nazar Hussain: Update our spec test, and then try to cover up
Nazar Hussain: And these were identified during when I was working, enabling Tuggle OS.
Nazar Hussain: Spec test for the fast Confirmation?
Nazar Hussain: So hope after these are released, then all the Gloas stuff will be working right for us.
Mikhail Kalinin: Nice.
Mikhail Kalinin: But you already have a release, right? So it works fine on the mainnet, it works correctly, right?
Nazar Hussain: Yeah, yeah, it's worked fine. These are just, like, few spec tests, and I digged further, and it was just the issue with the vectors, not with the implementation.
Nazar Hussain: So, I have a few spec tests disabled in our CI for now. The implementation is working fine, but once these, lay tests
Nazar Hussain: release is done for the spec test, and I will update our CI as well, to have run all the spec tests for Boscom Commission.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right, and yeah, and this Gloas update is, like, basically a Gloas thing, right? So, we are fine with that.
Nazar Hussain: Great. We are good with it.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yep, thanks a lot, Nazar.
Nazar Hussain: Thank you.
Mikhail Kalinin: Next.
Mikhail Kalinin: Next reason.
Jun Song: Yep, so I can give a short update from Prysm. So, we don't have a lot of things to update, but, I confirmed that, we at the FCR branch.
Jun Song: is passing the latest or a nightly spec test that, we, that the Consensus specs are serving. So, during that, I found a couple of
Jun Song: test generation bugs, and with, those fixes, I, confirmed that, our implementation passes the spec test, and we didn't have, run, those FCR features in mainnet or DevNet so far.
Jun Song: I think, we need a couple of more, deep review for our implementation, even though we passed this old backtests. So, that's all.
Mikhail Kalinin: Makes sense. Thanks a lot, and thanks for the PRs to fix, those couple of tests.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, they also merged.
Mikhail Kalinin: Just… maybe today.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright, cool.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, Teku.
Dmitrii Shmatko: Yeah, we continue to merge, feature FCR branch to the master.
Dmitrii Shmatko: You know, smaller chunks.
Dmitrii Shmatko: It will take another 2 weeks or three, we are in the middle, pound a few bucks while merging it in smaller parts.
Dmitrii Shmatko: And, that's all.
Mikhail Kalinin: Cool, did you manage to find the reason, behind the comparison failure with Lighthouse?
Dmitrii Shmatko: Yeah, not yet. I will recheck it today, because I, I had…
Dmitrii Shmatko: We have added a few fixes which could change behavior like this. Maybe it's already fixed, I will run it today.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay, nice. How much time…
Mikhail Kalinin: Does it take for you to run these comparison tests?
Dmitrii Shmatko: Like, 50 minutes or something like this.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay Yeah, that's… that's good, I think.
Mikhail Kalinin: By the way, while we are here, like,
Mikhail Kalinin: I have a question to… to…
Mikhail Kalinin: Jun may be. Have you tried this, tool from EthPandaOps?
Mikhail Kalinin: to compare your implementation to maybe Lighthouse or Lodestar.
Jun Song: You mean the FCR simulator?
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, yeah, yeah, this one.
Jun Song: Not yet.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, I was just, you know, asking, because, yeah, it was an interest from your side, last time, last call. Okay, cool.
Mikhail Kalinin: All right, thanks a lot for the updates.
Mikhail Kalinin: Before we move on to the next…
Mikhail Kalinin: Any… anything else, by the way? Any other updates here from the client's implementation side?
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay, cool. We'll move on to the next one. Autos, welcome to the FCR call.
Mikhail Kalinin: This is here.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, the next is, Glamster Dam DevNet Testing.
Mikhail Kalinin: This is the report by EthPandaOps.
Mikhail Kalinin: Which is… Which is great.
Mikhail Kalinin: I believe you have already seen this, just wanted to share here. And Barnabas, if you want to add anything on top of that.
Mikhail Kalinin: Please feel free to.
Barnabas: Well, we are just waiting for the implementation from President Takubmin.
Barnabas: I would say.
Mikhail Kalinin: Great, these, DevNets tests, Was, were very helpful.
Mikhail Kalinin: To find some issues with, like, specific laws,
Mikhail Kalinin: Clause, behavior around fast confirmations.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright.
Mikhail Kalinin: Let's move on to the next one. So the next one would be the client comparison on historical data. We were planning to have, to use the FCR simulator, and, once we have all implementations.
Mikhail Kalinin: Once we have all clients,
Mikhail Kalinin: Equipped with the production-grade implementation of fast Confirmation Rule.
Mikhail Kalinin: We were discussing that it will make sense to…
Mikhail Kalinin: To basically run the, this simulator, these simulations again, and compare, do the comparison tests.
Mikhail Kalinin: Of different implementations.
Mikhail Kalinin: I believe it's still a thing.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, but I think that we should wait for, for, basically, for Prysm and Teku.
Mikhail Kalinin: To… to… to basically add them to… to these… To this harness.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, we'll just follow up.
Mikhail Kalinin: on that.
Mikhail Kalinin: Asynchronously.
Mikhail Kalinin: Once, once, yeah, once the prison deck already, I'll just basically ask if Panda opts to do these simulations again.
Mikhail Kalinin: And see what it gives to us.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right.
Mikhail Kalinin: I just wanted to mention that this is still a PIN.
Mikhail Kalinin: The next is backend tests.
Mikhail Kalinin: So… There are… Yeah, there is a… there are a bunch of PRs here.
Mikhail Kalinin: you can find them in the agenda. This PR is basically… has been merged, so this should cover the Gloas issue as well, where the safe execution block hash is
Mikhail Kalinin: Mistakenly passed.
Mikhail Kalinin: from the current… From the most recent confirmed block, but not from its parent.
Mikhail Kalinin: So one of the… this was one of the main goals of having this PR. And, the rest,
Mikhail Kalinin: PRs are basically fixes to… To… to the fast confirmation test, and, to…
Mikhail Kalinin: the tests with the disabled BLS in general.
Mikhail Kalinin: Thanks, guys, for submitting those PRs. That was… Yeah, pretty useful.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay.
Mikhail Kalinin: Any questions on the tests and the spec?
Mikhail Kalinin: I'll just post the R's to the chat.
Mikhail Kalinin: Cool.
Mikhail Kalinin: The next item is fuzz… fuzzing client and limitations.
Mikhail Kalinin: On the previous call, that Lion basically raised this topic.
Mikhail Kalinin: to… Understand if there is an interest in FOSIN implementations?
Mikhail Kalinin: Which is actually… We decided to basically think about it.
Mikhail Kalinin: Or till the today's call.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, any thoughts on that?
Mikhail Kalinin: Except for that it would be quite useful, but…
Mikhail Kalinin: How much do… do you guys think this is important?
Mikhail Kalinin: For your implementations.
Justin Traglia: Alternative… alternatively, I was thinking that we could ask the security team to spin up their, agent swarm.
Justin Traglia: On the FCR implementations?
Justin Traglia: I mean, it's not fuzzing, but it's…
Mikhail Kalinin: Yep.
Justin Traglia: Like, agent buzzing, in a way.
Justin Traglia: If that's something you're interested in, we can ping them.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright, cool. Being Justin.
Mikhail Kalinin: about agents, agents,
Justin Traglia: Yeah, you should… Yeah, you should reach out to Nikos from the security team.
Mikhail Kalinin: Thanks, Justin.
Mikhail Kalinin: As for me, fuzzing would be a really important thing.
Mikhail Kalinin: But, it depends on… On, basically, the capacity.
Mikhail Kalinin: and bandwidths.
Mikhail Kalinin: Of the team that will handle this.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, I, yeah, I see a lot of, you know.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, I can say that that would be important, but yeah, that's just my opinion here.
Mikhail Kalinin: Because even though we have a good test coverage, some edge cases might still be there.
Mikhail Kalinin: That are not covered with the destined suit, best suit.
Mikhail Kalinin: Which could be found in fuzzing.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, basically.
Mikhail Kalinin: client comparison on mainnet historical data. This is kind of like… it's not fuzz, it's not differential fuzzing, but it's some kind of, like, test that will basically compare, and we'll try to
Mikhail Kalinin: We'll attempt to highlight some.
Mikhail Kalinin: Anomalies and behavior… different behaviors in clients, and potentially identify some bugs.
Mikhail Kalinin: So… Alright, if anything, if any thoughts on the fuzzin, please just post in the Telegram group.
Mikhail Kalinin: We can discuss it there.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright, well, let's… Move on to… to the next item.
Mikhail Kalinin: On the previous call, on the last call, we have been discussing the, save block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: Set to finalized instead of justified, when the bus Confirmation is disabled.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, any thoughts on that?
Mikhail Kalinin: Should we make this into the spec?
Mikhail Kalinin: So for the context, the reason to do this is basically, so we have a fast confirmation, which falls back to finality.
Mikhail Kalinin: And if the fast Confirmation is enabled, it's, it's, it will…
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, the save block hash will point out to either to finalized block or to the block that is
Mikhail Kalinin: Basically, yield by the fast Confirmation rule.
Mikhail Kalinin: There are just, you know, two things here. But EFAS Confirmation is disabled, and
Mikhail Kalinin: In this case, it will be… saved block hash will be basically a justified block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: And the justified block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: It's… its safety is questionable.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, that's the RTML for making this change.
Mikhail Kalinin: Any thoughts would be… Really appreciated on that.
Roberto Saltini: Just wonder whether… There aren't any users that…
Roberto Saltini: It's safe to mean justify, so rely on the fact that this…
Roberto Saltini: Most of the time, it's just one e-book behind, rather than two.
Roberto Saltini: I mean, I cannot… I wonder if there are some weird scenarios… there is some weird scenario where…
Roberto Saltini: -Oh.
Roberto Saltini: Using finalized instead.
Roberto Saltini: Bright things, just because of the extra e-book.
Roberto Saltini: Not sure.
Roberto Saltini: But they, you know… Not, not, not, not applying these changes, also.
Roberto Saltini: Not great, because of… yeah.
Roberto Saltini: because of the difference, so I…
Roberto Saltini: I didn't have a good answer.
Roberto Saltini: I don't know if anyone… Didn't see any… an issue.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, I… I actually… a bit helpful in making this change, whether it makes sense, and also.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, because… We don't know, basically, justified block hashes.
Mikhail Kalinin: used by anyone. I mean, like, safe block hash is used to derive the justified block hash. This is kind of still a bit of an open question here.
Mikhail Kalinin: So probably it makes sense to… Do these change?
Mikhail Kalinin: A little bit later, or…
Mikhail Kalinin: When the, pass Confirmation… when we get more, understanding of
Mikhail Kalinin: Whether this is the case, if anyone uses a block hash to get the justified block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: If any thoughts on that, please, yeah.
Mikhail Kalinin: Potuz, you mean you don't send justified, but you send unrealized justified, right?
potuz: Yep.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, it's still, like, more fresh, more recent, block than the, finalized block.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, the safety…
potuz: Safety assumption of unrealized justified is the same as of justified.
potuz: And a client will not reorg either of them, if there is… Synchrony.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right.
Roberto Saltini: That…
Mikhail Kalinin: That's true.
Roberto Saltini: That's true, only if… analyze, justified is from the previous e-book, and they are not to…
Roberto Saltini: To towards the end of the e-book.
Roberto Saltini: Bye.
potuz: No, but the safety assumption is the same. If… if you are… the only way to reorg either of them is on a period of asynchrony.
potuz: So, if there's no safety…
potuz: there's no safety benefit into using justified versus unrealized justified. It's true that finalized has a bigger safety assumption.
potuz: Well, has a less…
Roberto Saltini: I agree, I agree there is no… I agree that there is no difference between…
Roberto Saltini: Analyze, justified, and justified, yes. That's true.
Roberto Saltini: Yeah, what I was saying, that if the rely is justified, all justified is from, let's say.
Roberto Saltini: Three epochs ago, it's not really safe.
Roberto Saltini: Because there could be some hidden…
Roberto Saltini: Conflicting checkpoint from the previous epoch, for example.
Roberto Saltini: That showed up during a synchrony, now… now we are under synchrony.
Roberto Saltini: That is, like, almost justifies a point.
Roberto Saltini: Formed in the past.
Roberto Saltini: During a period of asynchrony?
Roberto Saltini: Yeah, so that's what I was saying, but I do agree that
Roberto Saltini: If you're okay with justified, we're also okay with our lies justified.
Mikhail Kalinin: Aye?
Mikhail Kalinin: thing that…
Mikhail Kalinin: By default, I would not make this change for the reason that if there are users of a saved block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: That, and they should be aware of the fast Confirmation rule.
Mikhail Kalinin: And they should actually, run their nodes with the feature flag that enables fast Confirmation rule, so… I…
Mikhail Kalinin: Don't…
Mikhail Kalinin: I think it's gonna be a problem, for… for them, you know, if we don't do this change.
Mikhail Kalinin: Oh, right.
Roberto Saltini: What about, though, like, RPC users that connect to RPC providers.
Roberto Saltini: You know, they might not be in control of which flag has been used.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, that's… a good point, but I hope that RPC providers
Mikhail Kalinin: We'll make this right, the thing right, so if they serve save block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: It also should be coming from the fast Confirmation Rule.
Mikhail Kalinin: What do you think?
Roberto Saltini: Yeah, not sure, but, you know… Seems that, you know.
Roberto Saltini: Any decision has its own drawback, so I have to say which one is.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, I just see that the fast Confirmation rule deprecates the previous approach to, you know, to…
Mikhail Kalinin: to actually serve in these, save-Blockache stuff. Yeah, potuz?
potuz: So there's one… one situation in which,
potuz: it might be different to serve the fast Confirmation rule than justified or finalized, and it's just that the surface for client bugs is much higher.
potuz: And… and the time to catch them, it's much shorter. So it's… the change to give either justified is just stateful, and you have it in the state. And if there's a bug, then the whole client is already in a consensus bug.
potuz: So, it's pretty safe to be sure that if your RPC provider is giving you the justified checkpoint, it is actually justified. If it's giving you the unrealized justified checkpoint, there's… there might be a bug, but still, again, those paths are very short, are very small. So it's unlikely to have a bug.
potuz: But, I mean, this fast Confirmation rule, it's been tested, it's a very large change, it changes… it requires a full new fork choice implementation.
potuz: I'm not sure if I am a large, like, roll-up, relying on this for deposits.
potuz: I'm not sure if I want to switch quickly to fast Confirmation versus using justify for a while.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right, I see, that's a fair point. But we've been trying to get the understanding around whether anyone is using justified BlockHash.
potuz: Oh.
potuz: I can give you one data point. Perhaps they moved back to finalized, but at least for a few months, Arbitrum was using SAFE,
potuz: for deposits.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, yeah, I can recall that. That was on… after one of the calls where we were trying to
Mikhail Kalinin: To actually, yeah, facilitate this discussion around the usage of safe block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: Before… before we introduce fast Confirmation.
Mikhail Kalinin: And Arbitrum basically was saying that,
Mikhail Kalinin: They're gonna be fine with switching to… with switching to finalize, but yeah, I don't know.
Mikhail Kalinin: Whether it has happened or not.
Mikhail Kalinin: But I believe that Arbitrum, Runs their own nodes, right, to, gets… disinformation.
potuz: Oh, yeah, yeah, so I doubt there's an RPC provider of this. I'm sorry, an RPC user of this.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yep.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, actually, if you… if you run… if you run a client which, there is only one client, as far as I am concerned, that enabled this feature by default, which is Nimbus.
Mikhail Kalinin: Other clients have a feature flag.
Mikhail Kalinin: So if you run a client with a picture flag, Must be that.
Mikhail Kalinin: Clearly understand what the implications are.
Mikhail Kalinin: So I think, yeah, from that perspective, it's still kind of looking fine.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright, thanks a lot for…
Mikhail Kalinin: discussion around this, and yeah, if anything, please just, you know, drop it in the Telegram group.
Mikhail Kalinin: We can discuss it there asynchronously.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, the next item is kind of related to safe block hash as well.
Mikhail Kalinin: There was a… There was a… Kind of…
Mikhail Kalinin: not an edge case, but the case that Deplian mentioned.
Mikhail Kalinin: On the previous call as well. So what should we serve as a safe block hash when CL node is down?
Mikhail Kalinin: And, right, or just recently started up.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, in this situation, save block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: will be… Capture it by the execution layer client.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, until the EL node, starts up, and,
Mikhail Kalinin: Catches up with the head and restarts the first confirmation chain. So these save-block hash will be kind of stale on the EL side.
Mikhail Kalinin: But, We should also consider the fact that
Mikhail Kalinin: It does not make this safe block.
Mikhail Kalinin: unsafe, I mean, like, this situation.
Mikhail Kalinin: So under… if the assumptions that we are making on the synchrony and adversarial power, kept
Mikhail Kalinin: The safe block will still remain safe, so it will not be locked out.
Mikhail Kalinin: So I think that, yeah, that's a good point to think on what could be done here, but I don't know. I would say that, I think using saved BlockHash is still
Mikhail Kalinin: Good enough in this case.
Mikhail Kalinin: Roberto, maybe you have other opinion on that.
Roberto Saltini: I mean, you said that using safe-procache is fine in this case? You mean until the… until we catch up? Until the CA catches up?
Mikhail Kalinin: Yes.
Roberto Saltini: And what would be… what would the alternative be, though, like that?
Mikhail Kalinin: The alternative is basically, yeah, once EL node is down, it doesn't seem like EL will understand that it's down, and, will do some fallback. We'll do any fallback.
Mikhail Kalinin: So before… before they restart, before the actual startups of a CL node, EL cannot do much here. But when the CL node is start up.
Mikhail Kalinin: By default, it will reset.
Mikhail Kalinin: It depends on the implementation, I believe.
Mikhail Kalinin: But by default, it will reset the saved block hash to the finalized block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, after a short restart, when, say, the upgrade of a CL node is happening.
Mikhail Kalinin: After a restart, after this upgrade is done.
Mikhail Kalinin: There probably will be a reset from saved Bot Cash to finalized Bot Cash, which might be…
Mikhail Kalinin: a bit behind, you know, I mean, the finalizable cache, so it's resetting the save block back.
Mikhail Kalinin: In time.
Roberto Saltini: Hmm.
Mikhail Kalinin: So if client… yeah, if client implementations, I don't know how much time it usually takes to upgrade your node.
Mikhail Kalinin: Or, you know… If it takes, like, more than 2 epochs, then it's probably fine.
Mikhail Kalinin: In most of the cases, finalized block will be advanced. If not, then we have other problems in the network.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, it's fine to fall back to finalized in this case.
Mikhail Kalinin: But yeah, if it takes less than two epochs, then we will see resets, too.
Mikhail Kalinin: A blog that is older.
Mikhail Kalinin: And yeah, that could be, should lead to bad UX.
Roberto Saltini: Hmm.
Mikhail Kalinin: Potuz?
potuz: There's more nuance than just the two epochs. So there are several ways in which node operators restart a CL client.
potuz: So if you keep your GB and you restart, you… so the client might start from the previous head.
potuz: And clients, like… there are some clients, like Lighthouse, for example, that would download… and I think Teku does the same, Dmitrii can tell me otherwise. But I think they download the full fork choice to disk.
potuz: And then, they pick it up, and they pick it up from head. So in that case, the fast block will be stale on the… on the CL, but they could just give the same.
potuz: Some other clients, like Prism, would just fall back to the last finalized checkpoint that they saved.
potuz: And that will be a reversal, regardless if the finalized checkpoint has advanced on mainnet.
potuz: And then if you do a checkpoint sync, then of course, if you do a checkpoint sync with the latest finalized, then it would be what you just said. But I think it's hard to cover all cases.
potuz: Perhaps the simplest would be for the
potuz: for the EL to recognize that it's falling back to a previous safe head.
Mikhail Kalinin: But how would the EL recognize this?
Mikhail Kalinin: Or you mean, like, to recognize this and ignore?
potuz: Right, it's going to be… it's going to… the CL will start… in one of these scenarios, the CL will start and send back the previous finalized hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, I see.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, thanks for sharing this.
Mikhail Kalinin: So at least it's gonna be implementation dependent, or we do something with EL, which is… Kind of… Like…
Mikhail Kalinin: Kind of difficult, you know, to…
Mikhail Kalinin: It's gonna be a hard sell, I believe.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay.
Mikhail Kalinin: So, but, Roberto, what do you think if client implementation
Mikhail Kalinin: Keeps the, save block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: Oh, sorry, yeah, so, sorry, confirmed route, if it caches the confirmed route.
Mikhail Kalinin: From before they restart.
Mikhail Kalinin: Do you think this is, like, a safe behavior?
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, and use this confirmed route after the restart.
Roberto Saltini: But, like, it… mmm…
Roberto Saltini: depends how long it takes to restart. Like, because the synchron assumption on that, whatever is confirmed is the synchron started
Roberto Saltini: No later than France.
Roberto Saltini: Three books ago?
Roberto Saltini: So, you know, if we confirm the block 5 epochs ago, now our assumption is that Synchrony started 7 epochs ago.
Roberto Saltini: But wait, but…
potuz: But the confirm block cannot roll back, right?
potuz: Even if we lose synchrony, We wouldn't roll back that confirmed block.
potuz: Yeah, we'll fail.
Roberto Saltini: No, we… There are conditions under which we… Go back to… to…
Roberto Saltini: Personalized, because we cannot trust that that block is safe anymore.
Roberto Saltini: At the moment.
Roberto Saltini: Like, if your block is older than 3 books, then we revert to formalized, for example. If the confirmed block is older than 3 books.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right.
Roberto Saltini: lost.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, it's just in the algorithm.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, I see.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay.
Roberto Saltini: I don't know, it is a tricky one, like, it's a very…
Roberto Saltini: It's also very hard to specify, because it's about the interaction between EL and… Yeah, post.
Roberto Saltini: Yeah.
Roberto Saltini: I mean, in most of the cases, we'll be fine.
Roberto Saltini: Because, actually, you have synchrony.
Roberto Saltini: We rarely ever asynchronous, so… In practice, I think.
Roberto Saltini: Is that a big issue?
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, then if we want to, actually have this behavior, that the, confirmed route is cached.
Mikhail Kalinin: Then we will have to… Then the implementations will have to… wait for…
Mikhail Kalinin: Do not run the fast Confirmation rule.
Mikhail Kalinin: Before the start… the new starting point, right?
Mikhail Kalinin: Otherwise, algorithmically, it just will roll back to the finalized block hash.
Mikhail Kalinin: In most of the cases.
Mikhail Kalinin: Because the saved block hash will stale and be older than two e-books.
Mikhail Kalinin: So it's like, yeah, as you said, it's gonna be, like, tweaking the algorithm.
Mikhail Kalinin: Or tweaking the implementation.
Roberto Saltini: Yeah, let me see…
potuz: Wouldn't it be an automatic rollback if the EL takes care of this?
potuz: I mean, the EL can know when the fast confirm block is older than two epochs.
potuz: So they could just roll back to finalize. They do have the finalized checkpoint already cached.
potuz: So they can do this rollback themselves.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yes, but currently it's in the algorithm anyway, so CL will do this.
potuz: Yeah, I understand, but the point is that if the CL is down, the EL can have only this little piece of this algorithm. If the EL is down, the EL can serve the stale one up to two epochs, and then suddenly realize, oh no, I need to fall back to finalized.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, I see. But it's not gonna serve the problem of, you know, resetting the save block hash.
potuz: Yeah, it will, because when you restart, when you restart the node, if you restart the node with your head, and you restart it, like, over two epochs from now, then the EL already took care of, like, falling back to finalized.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right, but I believe the original issue that we tried to think about here is the UX issue, when you basically restarted a node and your save block hash was reset back in time.
Mikhail Kalinin: If EL does this, then effectively this will…
potuz: No, the EL will not. If you just restart your node immediately, then the EL will not fall back to finalize, because two epochs haven't passed.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah. Alright, I see what you mean.
Roberto Saltini: Because it's an issue that…
Roberto Saltini: If we restart the CL, the CL will roll back to finalized regardless, because that's what we do when we start.
Roberto Saltini: But none of the nonsense.
potuz: really, like, Lighthouse would just keep the head.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right, but if they restart took less time than two epochs, then this reset will not happen.
Mikhail Kalinin: Only as well.
Mikhail Kalinin: And if EL keeps the confirmed route cached and starts with this confirmed route, it will be still served to the EL.
potuz: And that's a good one, right? If two epochs haven't passed, then this one is still confirmed.
Roberto Saltini: Yeah.
Roberto Saltini: Yep.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright.
Roberto Saltini: Yeah, yeah, so, but this is not how it is specified, it is implemented now, right?
Roberto Saltini: We're not caching at all.
Mikhail Kalinin: I… don't know, maybe?
Mikhail Kalinin: developers can ask… answer to this question. Do you cache the confirmed route, or do you, restart every time?
Mikhail Kalinin: the Confirmation rule.
potuz: I haven't looked at Terrence's code, but I'm pretty sure we're gonna restart it, because we don't… we don't restart from head.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
potuz: We don't download our fork choice to… to…
potuz: We don't upload our forges to the database.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, I see.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay, so…
potuz: Lighthouse made, because Lighthouse actually saves the full fork choice, so… I don't know what they do on the first Confirmation, but they… when they start up, they… they do pick their latest saved fork choice.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right, I see. Okay, so…
Mikhail Kalinin: It seems safe to use the confirmed route that is cached, and that is not…
Mikhail Kalinin: Older than 2 epochs ago?
Mikhail Kalinin: If it will be older than 2 epochs ago, then the algorithm will reset it to finalized block.
Mikhail Kalinin: This is something that, to keep in mind for the users of the FCR, then.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, yeah, implementations may actually cache the confirmed route. This is, like, three things that I can conclude from our discussion today.
Mikhail Kalinin: Please correct me if I'm wrong.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, also, this behavior… the cache in confirmed route is going to be implementation dependent. This is the… the other thing.
Mikhail Kalinin: Because not all clients, basically, dump their fork choice state… fork choice store to… to disk.
Mikhail Kalinin: ELS, EL can also fall back, but this is gonna be the EL change, which…
Mikhail Kalinin: I would try to avoid, if possible.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright.
Mikhail Kalinin: The next one is fast Confirmation Post Clause. So, what we have been discussing recently as well is that,
Mikhail Kalinin: In Gloas, we cannot confirm the…
Mikhail Kalinin: The block from the previous slot, as we do before those.
Mikhail Kalinin: This is because of the new… slot structure.
Mikhail Kalinin: So the DAS confirmed block will be from 2 slots ago.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, we were also… considering… Doing some…
Mikhail Kalinin: improvement to the algorithm using PTC votes in order to Consumed the,
Mikhail Kalinin: A more fresh payload, which is, yeah, the payload from the previous slot.
Mikhail Kalinin: As… to actually provide, to actually support the same behavior as before Gloas.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, yeah.
Mikhail Kalinin: but there are complexities, and this is a change to the algorithm.
Mikhail Kalinin: so, it doesn't seem like an easy thing to do.
Mikhail Kalinin: Potuz?
potuz: I guess Roberto is here, but I don't believe you guys can use PTC for anything like this.
potuz: Ptc will not attest for validity, so…
potuz: I would be very skeptical that PTC would allow you to
potuz: To… to say something about the previous one.
Mikhail Kalinin: Right, but if you have validity, if you have a local validity…
potuz: You will have validity already of the previous one because of the attestations of the current block, but still, I'll be skeptical of using PTC for this.
potuz: Also, I don't think the semantics changes in Gloas. You're talking about slots, but… but the block that is confirmed is exactly the same as pre-GLAS. You're confirming the last block before
potuz: So the previous last block that is being attested.
potuz: Which is still the same. It's exactly the same as before.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yep, this is correct.
Mikhail Kalinin: But I think what matters for… for… Research is the confirmed payload.
Mikhail Kalinin: Not… not a block, so…
potuz: Yeah, when I say block, I mean payload. So you're always confirming the previous to the last payload that has been attested.
potuz: attestations at N are for the payload of N-1, so you're always…
potuz: Confirming the previous to the last payload.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yes, but we run the fast confirmation rule at the start of N plus 1.
Mikhail Kalinin: So we… at the start of N plus 1, we confirm a payload… we confirm a Beacon block from N-1, from N, and the payload from n-1.
Mikhail Kalinin: This is how it currently works.
potuz: Yeah, which is the payload, the latest payload, that was attested.
Mikhail Kalinin: I see what you mean, yes, I agree.
potuz: So the problem is that…
Mikhail Kalinin: Congratulations.
potuz: attestations are delayed, but the payload that you're confirming is exactly the same.
Mikhail Kalinin: I see.
Roberto Saltini: Yeah, the thing is that you don't… you're not confirming the… Fullness or emptiness of the… Right.
Roberto Saltini: That's the difference that you need.
Roberto Saltini: Alright.
potuz: Right, so you should think of attestation-sRN plus 1,
potuz: From the point of view of this, as an attestation for the payload of N.
potuz: So instead of thinking of them as attestation for the CL block of N plus 1, you're thinking of them as just attestations for the payload of N.
Roberto Saltini: That's what… Causes, say, an extra slot of delay to confirm the inclusion of a transaction.
potuz: Yeah, it should be half a slot, but yeah, so you, you could… But yes, that's correct.
Roberto Saltini: Yeah, that's why we're thinking.
Roberto Saltini: Perhaps the PTC can be used to…
Roberto Saltini: To, yeah, to reduce this delay.
potuz: I think it's gonna be.
Roberto Saltini: Like, we have a.
potuz: shrinky with PTC, it's…
potuz: it might be… it might be very, very tricky. Like, there are some things that will cause a reorg. For example, if… if the payload takes too long to come… to execute. I mean, these kind of guarantees, we don't… we don't really have.
potuz: But if… if a payload takes…
potuz: And perhaps you should actually take this into account in the proof of the fast Confirmation rule, but if a payload takes more than the time allotted to execute.
potuz: I think currently it causes an ex-ante reorg.
potuz: So it doesn't… I think it doesn't change the things that have been already confirmed.
potuz: But I think it would just, like, screw up with the fast confirmation on the next block.
potuz: And these kind of things cannot be seen by the PTC.
Mikhail Kalinin: Let's see.
Mikhail Kalinin: So it's… it's gonna be tricky, and… potentially unsafe.
Mikhail Kalinin: to rely on PTC, right?
potuz: I cannot… I can't find a bug in relying on the PTC now. Everything that I… I mean, if I can think of anything, it's going to be about, like, the next block, not about the one that you're confirming now.
potuz: But… but there are some subtleties to PTC. One of them is that PTC does not attest to validity, and it could be that the payload takes longer to execute, and it reords the next block, and it could be that the proposer doesn't have the data, but the PTC says that it exists.
potuz: So… I don't know.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay, I see.
Mikhail Kalinin: Then, EIP proposer… And have the data, then the, the empty proposal will be… Revolved, right, by a.
potuz: Yeah, so all of the cases that I'm showing are cases in which the next proposal will be reorged, so in principle, it shouldn't affect the confirmed log, but it will affect the confirmation rule in the next log.
Mikhail Kalinin: Okay, I see Alright.
Mikhail Kalinin: Anyway, so this… this seems to be quiet.
Mikhail Kalinin: Difficult thing to… to do.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, yeah.
Roberto Saltini: Most of them will be, like, spec test work, and spec work, and…
Roberto Saltini: Yeah. Like, even if we can't believe that.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright.
Mikhail Kalinin: Anyway, good to… Have this flagged.
Mikhail Kalinin: Have a discussion around this.
Mikhail Kalinin: And, yeah, another, another, another thing is that, there is a work in progress on decoupled Consensus.
Mikhail Kalinin: And decoupled Consensus will come with its own confirmation rule.
Mikhail Kalinin: Which basically… deprecates the FCR, the current version of the FCR?
Mikhail Kalinin: And doing this improvement, given that it's quite,
Mikhail Kalinin: resourceful, like, resource-consuming, might not be, yeah, might not be reasonable.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright, the last point is, like, is research updates. Do we have research… any research updates for today?
Roberto Saltini: No.
Roberto Saltini: But we didn't also expect any of that.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yep.
Roberto Saltini: The part is concluded.
Mikhail Kalinin: Cool. That's great. Thanks, Roberto.
Mikhail Kalinin: Alright, before we wrap up, anything else to discuss or share today?
Mikhail Kalinin: Great, thanks a lot. Yeah, as I mentioned in the beginning, this is going to be the last recurring call.
Mikhail Kalinin: If any… anything… anything in the future we want to discuss, that will demand a call, we can set up an ad hoc one.
Mikhail Kalinin: We made a great progress.
Mikhail Kalinin: So far. So, thanks everyone for attending these calls. Thanks, everyone, for, you know, participating in all these.
Mikhail Kalinin: Great stuff.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, wasn't… Great project, and yeah, let's continue and follow up in Telegram.
Mikhail Kalinin: Yeah, yeah, yeah, Potuz.
potuz: See you guys!
Mikhail Kalinin: Deal.
Roberto Saltini: Yeah.
Mikhail Kalinin: Bye.
Dmitrii Shmatko: And goodbye.
Jun Song: Alright, cheers, bro.